Guide to the Al cantío de un gallo Radio Program Audio Recordings
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Tape 103, 1994 December 9; 1 (Box 103)
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. The conversation continues on the topic of human rights abuses in Cuba. They talk about the United Nations inspector who tried to go to Cuba without success and how he met with representatives from many NGOs and international organizations to discuss the Cuban situation. Then, they read reports of people who have been arrested for crimes such as promoting enemy propaganda or criticizing the government.
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Crisis de derechos humanos en Cuba. Franqui y Melero notan que los derechos humanos son violados constantemente en la Cuba de Castro. Aunque Castro no dejó entrar a un relator de la ONU, el relator pudo producir un reporte criticando severamente a Cuba por sus violaciones de los derechos humanos, ya que muchos cubanos han denunciado estas violaciones en el exterior. La ONU recomienda que Cuba libere a prisioneros políticos y permita la entrada de la ONU.
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Más preocupaciones por los derechos humanos en Cuba. La conversación sigue siendo sobre los derechos humanos en Cuba y las muchas violaciones a ellos. Hablan sobre el inspector de la ONU que no pudo entrar en Cuba y cuentan que se juntó con representantes de varias organizaciones de derechos humanos para discutir el tema de Cuba. Luego, leen varios reportes sobre gente que ha sido arrestada en Cuba por crímenes como distribuir propaganda enemiga o criticar al gobierno.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 104, 1994 December 29; 1 (Box 104)
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Montijo, Amalia. The three speakers reminisce about the past year, 1994. They all agree that 1994 has been a terrible year for Cuba. It was marked by scarcity of goods, more militarization, less civic freedoms, and a collapsing economy. They say that all this is not socialism or communism, it is just Castro trying to stay in power - they call it fidelismo. They do note that faith has increased among Cubans. They hope that 1995 will bring freedom to Cuba.
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Montijo, Amalia. As they continue remembering 1994, the speakers also begin to talk about other countries that have suffered from tyrannies, noting that all of them have eventually fallen. Castro is the only dictator left in the Western world. Franqui notes that, like Asian countries, Cuba is implementing capitalist reforms to sustain communism and keep Castro in power. The only thing that keeps Cuba oppressed is Castro, his brother, and his corrupt group of cronies.
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Montijo, Amalia. Recordando 1994. Los tres locutores recuerdan los eventos que han sucedido en Cuba en 1994. Ha sido un año de escasez, de mayor militarización, de menos derechos humanos y de una economía muy mala. Dicen que todo esto no es ni socialismo ni comunismo, sino fidelismo. Notan que ha habido un renacimiento de fe entre los cubanos en 1994.
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Montijo, Amalia. Tiranía e ideología en Cuba. Mientras continúan recordando lo sucedido en 1994, los locutores también comienzan a hablar sobre otros países que también han sufrido de tiranías que eventualmente han caído. Sólo Castro queda como el único dictador del Oeste. Franqui nota que, así como en el Asia, Cuba está implementando reformas capitalistas para sostener el comunismo y mantener a Castro en poder. Lo único que mantiene Cuba en esta situación oprimida es Castro, su hermano y su camarilla de amigos.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 105, 1994 December 29; 1 (Box 105)
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Montijo, Amalia. In this episode, the speakers talk about the balseros that have been imprisoned in Guantanamo Bay by the United States, after the US changed its immigration policy, closing down its borders to Cubans. Though they criticize Clinton for this change, they say that the real culprit is Castro. Montijo says that the Guantanamo prisoners are paradoxically free and not free, prisoners in Cuba but not actually in Cuba.
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Montijo, Amalia. The speakers keep talking about Guantanamo. They complain that despite massive protests to release the Cubans there, President Clinton simply reacted by saying that they will improve conditions in the jails. Moreover, the promise that children would still be allowed to go into the US now seems about to be broken. Franqui says that Cubans are now alone in their search for freedom as more and more countries no longer give asylum to Cubans. The solution to all this is to bring change to Cuba. To do this, Cubans have to organize themselves and institute democracy.
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Montijo, Amalia. Los presos de Guantánamo. En este episodio los locutores hablan sobren los balseros que han sido encarcelados en la bahía de Guantánamo después que los Estados Unidos cambió su política de inmigración, así cerrando su frontera a los cubanos. Aunque critican a Clinton por esto, dicen que el verdadero culpable es Castro. Montijo dice que, paradójicamente, los prisioneros en Guantánamo son y no son libres, están presos en Cuba pero no están en Cuba.
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Montijo, Amalia. Más sobre Guantánamo y un llamado a la acción. Los locutores siguen hablando sobre Guantánamo. Se quejan de que a pesar de las masivas protestas sobre el tema, el presidente Clinton solamente ha prometido mejorar las condiciones de la cárcel. Para complicar más las cosas, la promesa que los niños todavía podrían entrar a Cuba parece a punto de romperse. Franqui dice que los cubanos ahora están solos en el mundo, ya que muchos países les están negando el asilo. La solución a todo esto, dicen, es traer cambio y democracia a Cuba. Para hacer esto, los cubanos tienen que organizarse, rebelarse e instituir la democracia en Cuba.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 106, 1995 January 1; 1 (Box 106)
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. It is New Year's Day and Melero asks Franqui to give his predictions for what will happen in Cuba in 1995. Franqui is somewhat pessimistic about the island's future, saying that Castro has generated too much fear, mistrust, and desperation. He is, however, hopeful because there have been more spontaneous protests and if there is enough popular revolt, the regime will fall because it is actually fragile, something people fail to recognize because of fear.
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Franqui draws much hope from the August protests, saying that if there are more protests like this one, Cuba will be free. He also believes that the movement for freedom will be led by the youth. He then talks about how Castro has taken over Jose Martí's philosophy, even though Martí was a fervent advocate of freedom. Finally, he points out that Havana will be the center of the rebellion against Castro.
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Predicciones para Cuba en 1995. Es el día del año nuevo y Melero le pide a Franqui que dé sus predicciones para Cuba en 1995. Franqui es un poco pesimista, diciendo que Castro ha generado mucho miedo, desconfianza y desesperación. Pero la presencia de protestas espontáneas le da mucha esperanza de que el régimen podría caer.
  Side B: Melero, Alfredo. Franqui, Carlos. Las posibilidades de libertad en 1995. A Franqui le da mucha esperanza la protesta masiva que ocurrió en La Habana en agosto y cree que si hay más protestas como ésta, Cuba será libre. Dice que todo depende de los jóvenes cubanos. Luego, habla de cómo Castro ha corrompido la filosofía de Martí, quien era devoto de la libertad. Finalmente, dice que él cree que la rebelión contra Castro nacerá en La Habana.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 107, Circa 1994-1998; 1 (Box 107)
  [Blank.]
- Tape 108, 1995 January 9; 1 (Box 108)
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Melero and Franqui point out various aspects of Castro that have discredited him in the international arena. First is his hypocrisy. He once said that when the people asked him to step down he would, but even after massive protests, he remains in power. Many of his human rights violations have come to the surface. Franqui and Melero hope that this will make tourists less likely to go to Cuba. They also note that many youth groups have started to organize themselves for armed rebellion against Castro because Castro has closed down all options for a peaceful dialogue.
  Side A: Melero, Alfredo. Franqui, Carlos. Desprestigio internacional de Castro y rebelión armada. Melero y Franqui describen varios aspectos de Castro que lo han desprestigiado, como su hipocrecía y sus muchas violaciones de los derechos humanos. Los locutores esperan que esto desaliente a los turistas de viajar a Cuba. Finalmente, notan que varios grupos de jóvenes se han armado y organizado para rebelarse contra Castro ya que él ha cerrado todas las vías al diálogo pacífico.
  - Preservation master, 1
  - Use copy, 1
- Tape 109, 1995 January 16; 1 (Box 109)
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Melero and Franqui begin by talking about how Cuban history has been marred by hurricanes, the Castro hurricane being the worst. Franqui feels as if they are in the eye of the storm because he feels a strange calm but knows that this will be followed by tumultuous times, either for the best or the worst. Then, they talk of how foreign countries, like Spain and Mexico, have hurt Cubans by siding with Castro. But, they say in the end, they will get what they deserve because Castro is a bad luck charm, which is why Mexico's economy is plummeting and they are having problems with guerrillas.
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Franqui and Melero discuss how AIDS has been spreading throughout Cuba because of all the sex tourism going on. They say people don't know much about AIDS or how to prevent it, mainly because Castro has been denying the presence of AIDS in Cuba for a long time. Tuberculosis and other diseases are also on the rise because of the lack of medicine and good food. They then talk about political prisoners and how the United Nations has asked for amnesty for them. Finally, they talk about the balseros imprisoned in Panama by the US and how the US is not helping the Cuban cause in this case.
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Huracanes políticos y la maldición de Castro. Melero y Franqui dicen que la historia cubana ha sido marcada por huracanes, el huracán de Castro siendo el peor. Franqui siente que están en el ojo del huracán ya que siente una extraña calma antes de un año que promete ser decisivo para Cuba. Luego, hablan de cómo varios países han desprestigiado al pueblo cubano, pero les llegará su merecido ya que Castro supuestamente trae mala suerte, la razón por la cual la economía Mexicana está colapsando.
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. De enfermedades y prisioneros políticos. Franqui y Melero discuten cómo el SIDA se ha propagado por Cuba debido al turismo sexual. La gente no sabe cómo prevenir el SIDA y el regimen castrista niega la presencia de esta enfermedad en Cuba. La tuberculosis y otras enfermedades han incrementado también debido a la falta de medicinas y comida. Luego, hablan de los prisioneros políticos y de la ONU que ha pedido amnistía para éstos. Finalmente, hablan sobre los balseros que están presos en Panamá y se quejan de que los Estados Unidos no está ayudando a Cuba en esta situación.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 110, 1995 January 16; 1 (Box 110)
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Melero starts by explaining that without sugar, there is no Cuba, which is why he is so worried that Castro has destroyed the sugar industry in the island. Sugar is so scarce that people now only get a pound of sugar for every three pounds they used to get. This is worrisome because sugar had always been abundant in Cuba.
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Melero and Franqui say they are sad because Cuba is alone in the world now that many countries are denying them asylum and refuge. They say it is because Cuba has fallen out of importance and now countries worry about protecting their borders. They accept, however, that Cuba cannot depend on others to survive - Cubans themselves have to bring about change. They call for people to engage in non-violent protests and evoke images of civic resistance in India and the Philippines.
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. La crisis del azúcar cubana. Melero comienza explicando que sin azúcar, no hay país, por lo que la reciente escasez de azúcar en la isla le es muy preocupante. Castro ha arruinado tanto la economía que ahora ni siquiera hay azúcar en un país en el que siempre ha habido una gran abundancia de ella.
  Side B: Melero, Alfredo. Franqui, Carlos. Un llamado a la resistencia pacífica. Melero y Franqui dicen estar tristes porque Cuba está sola en el mundo ahora que varios países ya no aceptan a cubanos como refugiados. Los locutores creen que es porque Cuba ya no es importante en el contexto político internacional. Ellos aceptan que sólo los cubanos pueden cambiar Cuba y por eso les hacen un llamado a que protesten pacíficamente, evocando imágenes de la resistencia civil en India y Filipinas.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 111, 1995 January 18; 1 (Box 111)
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Franqui and Melero talk about José Martí because of his upcoming birthday. They say that they will talk about what Martí really was - a great poet, creator of the basis of modernism, a lover of freedom - and not what they think of him. Other people read some of his poems. Then they play music for a while. In the second part of the recording, a speaker reads Martí's writings about the United States, its constitution and its history.
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. This recording has two parts to it. In both, they talk about José Martí and read excerpts from his works. They also read a biography of Martí and explain how Castro is trying to make him an accomplice in his revolution even though Martí's philosophy goes against all that Castro does. By reading excerpts from his works, the speakers attempt to prove that Martí was a proponent of democracy and a defender of freedom.
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Locutores no identificados. Celebrando a José Martí. Franqui y Melero hablan sobre José Martí ya que su cumpleaños se acerca. Exponen lo que Martí fue - gran poeta, creador de las bases del modernismo, amante de la libertad - y no lo que piensan de él. Otras personas leen algunos de sus poemas y luego ponen música por un buen rato. En la segunda parte de la grabación, un locutor lee de los textos de Martí sobre la historia y la constitución de Estados Unidos.
  Side B: Melero, Alfredo. Franqui, Carlos. Otro tributo a Martí. Esta grabación tiene dos partes. En ambas partes hablan de José Martí y leen extractos de sus obras. Leen una biografía de Martí y explican cómo ahora Castro lo ha hecho acómplice de su revolución cuando la filosofía de Martí va en contra de todo lo que ha hecho Castro. Al leer fragmentos de sus obras, Melero y Franqui tratan de demostrar que Martí era un proponente de la democracia y un defensor de la libertad.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 112, 1995 January 21; 1 (Box 112)
  Side A: Melero, Alfredo. Franqui, Carlos. Melero and Franqui continue praising José Martí. They say that one of the worst things Castro could have done was place Martí as a symbol of his regime, when his philosophy goes against everything Castro stands for. They call for Cubans to read Martí's work to understand what he really was about. They read more excerpts from Martí´s works, including one famous quote that says a country cannot be created like a military camp.
  Side B: Melero, Alfredo. Franqui, Carlos. Melero and Franqui continue discussing the life and philosophy of Martí. They talk about his years as a journalist and then read excerpts from various articles he wrote. One of them, a review of Herbert Spencer's work, reads as a portrait of modern Cuba, as it talks about abusive governments. Melero asserts that many of the books of Martí have been doctored by the Castro regime, so it is important to go to the original source.
  Side A: Melero, Alfredo. Franqui, Carlos. Más tributos a José Martí. Melero y Franqui continúan alabando a José Martí. Dicen que una de las peores cosas hechas por Castro ha sido poner a Martí como símbolo de su gobierno. Piden que los cubanos lean los textos de Martí para que entiendan lo qué Martí realmente era. Leen más fragmentos de su obra, incluyendo una cita famosa que dice que un pueblo no se funda al igual que se manda un campamento militar.
  Side B: Melero, Alfredo. Franqui, Carlos. Más lecturas de Martí. Melero y Franqui continúan discutiendo la vida y obra de Martí. Hablan sobre los años periodísticos de Martí y luego leen excerptos de sus artículos. Uno de ellos, una reseña de la obra de Herbert Spencer, lee como un retrato de la Cuba moderna, ya que habla sobre gobiernos abusivos. Melero dice que varios documentos de Martí han sido alterados por el régimen castrista, y recomienda que los cubanos busquen los textos originales.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 113, 1995 February 1; 1 (Box 113)
  Side A: Melero, Alfredo. Franqui, Carlos. Rodríguez, Felipe. Silva, Rodolfo. The speakers begin by commenting that they will only get bad news from Cuba until the day that Castro falls. Then, they read an article that explains how Cuba is being affected by the Mexican economic crisis. They note that every time there is a crisis in the world, Cuba suffers a lot because it is in such poor conditions. But, they explain that the crisis started with Castro. He is responsible for everything but always blames things on scapegoats.
  Side B: Melero, Alfredo. Franqui, Carlos. Silva, Rodolfo. Rodríguez, Felipe. The speakers comment on the soaring unemployment rates in Cuba and how an upcoming government policy will result in many more people getting laid off. This is happening because Cuba, without the support of the USSR, can no longer subsidize businesses that are not profitable. Many of these businesses will be closing down, and those unemployed will be offered agriculture jobs. The speakers note that Cuba is out of reserves and that this is something that should have happened 30 years ago but was postponed because of Soviet subsidies.
  Side A: Melero, Alfredo. Franqui, Carlos. Rodríguez, Felipe. Silva, Rodolfo. Una Cuba vulnerable ante crisis externas. Los locutores comienzan comentando que de Cuba solo recibirán malas noticias hasta el día que caiga Castro. Luego, leen un artículo que explica cómo Cuba está siendo afectada por la crisis económica mexicana. Notan que cada vez que hay una crisis en el mundo, Cuba termina sufriendo mucho debido a su condición muy frágil. Pero ellos explican que la crisis de Cuba comenzó con Castro y no con estas crisis externas. Él es responsable de todo, aunque siempre culpe a los demás.
  Side B: Melero, Alfredo. Franqui, Carlos. Silva, Rodolfo. Rodríguez, Felipe. Sin subsidios, Cuba cae. Los locutores comentan sobre los altos niveles de desempleo en Cuba y sobre una medida del gobierno que cerrará empresas que no son solventes y que dejará a muchos más sin empleo. Esto se debe a que Cuba, sin el apoyo de la Unión Soviética, no puede subsidiar a estas empresas no solventes. Los locutores dicen que esto debería haber ocurrido hace 30 años, pero fue evitado gracias a los subsidios soviéticos.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 114, 1995 February 1; 1 (Box 114)
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Silva, Rodolfo. Rodríguez, Felipe. Franqui tells of his recent trip to Washington D.C., where he met with different organizations to discuss Cuban issues. He had a meeting at the Atlantic Council to discuss Cuban-US relations, especially the United States' new rules regarding asylum policies and the Guantanamo balsero situation. Franqui also met with Radio Martí and notes that various radio broadcasts are being censored in the Havana area because of fears that they will incite popular unrest.
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Silva, Rodolfo. Rodriguez, Felipe. Franqui tells more about his trip to Washington D.C. He says how there are a lot of people in the United States (US) who are really interested in investing in the Cuban market once Castro is out, including big companies like Coca Cola and Pepsi. Then, they talk about different schemes Castro has for maintaining power, such as continuing with communism and probably changing the name of the communist party to evoke nationalism in times of crisis. Finally, they talk about how government journalists in Cuba have been arrested for going off script, such as a news presenter who was suspended for saying Merry Christmas, which is strictly prohibited.
  Side A: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Silva, Rodolfo. Rodríguez, Felipe. Franqui relata su viaje a Washington D.C. Carlos Franqui nos cuenta sobre su reciente viaje a la capital americana donde se reunió con varias organizaciones. En la reunión con el Consejo Atlántico, discutieron relaciones cubano-americanas. En Radio Martí discutieron el tema de la censura y como las radios están siendo bloqueadas en La Habana por miedo a que inciten a la rebelión.
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Silva, Rodolfo. Rodriguez, Felipe. Franqui en Washington, Castro manteniéndose en poder y la falta de libertades para la prensa. Franqui cuenta más sobre su viaje a Washington, especialmente sobre cómo muchos empresarios tienen gran interés en invertir en el mercado cubano una vez Castro se vaya, incluyendo compañías como Coca Cola y Pepsi. Luego hablan de cómo Castro pretende preservarse en el poder manteniendo el comunismo y tal vez cambiándole el nombre al partido comunista para evocar nacionalismo en tiempos de crisis. Finalmente, cuentan que algunos periodistas han sido arrestados por improvisar durante sus programas. Un presentador de noticias fue suspendido por decir Feliz Navidad al aire, algo estrictamente prohibido.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 115, 1995 February 8; 1 (Box 115)
  Side A: Melero, Alfredo. Franqui, Carlos. Melero and Franqui start by reading the news that Cuba is planning to build many houses to be sold to foreigners. They find this disturbing given that the money used for those houses could be used to fix many houses inhabited by Cubans that are in terrible condition. They then describe the bad infrastracture throughout Cuba, which results in fires and health problems. They talk about the hygiene problems in Cuba because there is no toothpaste, soap, or other hygiene products. Franqui believes that because Castro has taken so much from Cubans, once a revolt starts, it will receive massive popular support.
  Side B: Franqui, Carlos. Melero, Alfredo. Franqui and Melero read a letter that has been circulating around Cuba. It was written by a professor at a university in Cuba and is highly critical of the Castro regime. The letter says that power has been concentrated with Fidel Castro and the military and that Castro's ruling style is just like any other caudillo. The letter regrets the fact that the people have lost their power over their political future and calls for more popular representation. Finally, it notes that the lack of freedoms has made the country unable to provide basic goods.